<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: talks | mrjordangoldstein]]></title>
  <link href="http://mrjordangoldstein.com/blog/categories/talks/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mrjordangoldstein.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-04T22:41:40-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://mrjordangoldstein.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jordan Goldstein]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[mrjordangoldstein]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[hackNY Talks: Branch]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrjordangoldstein.com/blog/2013/06/04/hackny-talks-branch/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-04T02:07:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrjordangoldstein.com/blog/2013/06/04/hackny-talks-branch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This summer, I&rsquo;m fortunate to be a part of the <a href="http://hackny.org/">hackNY</a> 2013 Fellows program. As such, I will be attending a number of talks from people in and around the New York City startup scene. While I may not blog for each one, I&rsquo;ll probably post most of the highlights.</p>

<p>For the first of our talks this summer, we were treated to <a href="https://twitter.com/joshm">Josh Miller</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/hursh">Hursh Agrawal</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/gem_ray">Cemre Güngör</a>, founders of popular conversation platform Branch. They shared a number of helpful and often hilarious stories, as well as doing a fantastic hour long Q&amp;A session. Rather than post my personal reaction, or attempt to summarize everything they said, I&rsquo;d like to share a few short, memorable lessons I wrote down while listening. Keep in mind these are pieces of advice I flagged as being relevant specifically to me, and they do not in any way demonstrate the scope of their presentation. I do hope they give an inkling of the insight the talk offered, and perhaps help someone in need of their wisdom.</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>To get more out of meetings, go into them wanting someone&rsquo;s opinion, not trying to sell them.</li>
<li>To discern good feedback from bad, look for what common traits all of your feedback shares.</li>
<li>Consider someone&rsquo;s experiences, skillset, and bias when judging their feedback.</li>
<li>Turning an idea into a business is not a conscious decision. It happens naturally over time.</li>
<li>Be precise with what you want from people. A direct request is more likely to get a reply.</li>
<li>When you aren&rsquo;t your target user, the design process involves studying people who are.</li>
<li>One person loving your application is going to promote it much more than ten people liking it.</li>
<li>Let someone form their own opinion of your application, by actually interacting with it, before pitching them on it. Their feedback is both more honest and overall better this way.</li>
</ul>


<p>Keep in mind, as they did well to note, that their advice was offered specifically in reference to consumer web startups.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll end with a quote from the talk. It was both too funny and too true (in my opinion) not to share:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Doing your startup in San Fransisco is like being an investment banker in New York</p><footer><strong>Cemre Güngör</strong> <cite>hackNY Talk at Branch</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Interpret it as you will. In the coming days I plan to write on why this fact, and other elements of New York, resonate so well with me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
