<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: linguistics | mrjordangoldstein]]></title>
  <link href="http://mrjordangoldstein.com/blog/categories/linguistics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mrjordangoldstein.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-09T18:49:29-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://mrjordangoldstein.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jordan Goldstein]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[mrjordangoldstein]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improving Your Discussions by Enforcing Linguistic Clarity]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrjordangoldstein.com/blog/2013/09/09/improving-your-discussions-by-enforcing-linguistic-clarity/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-09T14:49:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrjordangoldstein.com/blog/2013/09/09/improving-your-discussions-by-enforcing-linguistic-clarity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wow, that&rsquo;s quite a title, isn&rsquo;t it? I&rsquo;m sure it will get all the hits. However, given that you&rsquo;re here, then for some reason, you&rsquo;ve decided to give me the benefit of the doubt. If you&rsquo;ll continue to do so for a moment, let me posit a theory:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The majority of ineffective human disagreements stem from linguistic problems, in that both parties use the same terms with different meanings.</p></blockquote></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Now, that&rsquo;s quite a lofty generalization. But what do I mean by it? Let me explain by demonstration. In this case, I&rsquo;ll use a conversation I&rsquo;ve heard over &ldquo;free software&rdquo; dozens of times:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Free Software Advocate: I believe that all software should be free.<br/>Participant: If software were free, no one would make any money, and no one would make software!</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Soon after this, Free Software Advocate will clarify that they mean free like the <a href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html">GNU Four Freedoms</a>—free to run as you please, modify, share, and share your modified copy. In fact, this particular instance of linguistic confusion is so incredibly common that free software advocates have a phrase to quickly clarify their meaning—"Free as in speech, not free as in beer". Luckily, in this case, this disagreement is discovered quite quickly. Based on a combination of the participant&rsquo;s response, and the advocates past experiences, the advocate is quickly able to identify the linguistic confusion and clarify the meaning. But the conversation doesn&rsquo;t stop there. Let us analyze a more insidious example.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Free Software Advocate: I believe that all software should be free—free to run as you please, to change, to share, and to share your changes.<br/>Participant: How can you make money if users can share copies of your software?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Quickly, the Free Software Advocate will begin to cite examples of companies like Red Hat or MongoDB<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, that provide access to the source code of their product, but make money selling support, hosting, or otherwise. Perhaps the Free Software Advocate will discuss their own life and history, in which they make a salary to produce free software. It&rsquo;s at this point that the conversation normally begins to degrade. This may take a variety of forms—increased volume of voices, exasperated sighs, responses that answer different questions than those asked by the other side, or in many cases, giving up on the discussion altogether. Normally, the Participant walks away thinking &ldquo;What does he or she not understand? That dirty hippie.&rdquo; while the Free Software Advocate walks away thinking &ldquo;What does he or she not understand? The vile capitalist.&rdquo; We&rsquo;re going to call this period of the conversation the &ldquo;Pit&rdquo;, during which the discussion degrades until coming to a sputtering halt. Why did we reach this Pit?</p>

<p>Because the Participant and the Free Software Advocate were using entirely different definitions for the phrase &ldquo;make money.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Often, in the case of the Free Software Advocate, &ldquo;make money&rdquo; meant &ldquo;make enough money to provide a livable wage and a comfortable lifestyle&rdquo;, while in the case of the participant, &ldquo;make money&rdquo; meant &ldquo;make the most amount of money possible off of this particular piece of software.&rdquo; These are entirely different concepts, and rarely does either side bring these details up! By leaving out these details, the conversation was inherently likely to end up in the &ldquo;Pit"—I&rsquo;ll call this a "Pit Trap&rdquo;. Let&rsquo;s reimagine this conversation once again, but handily avoid the Pit Trap.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Free Software Advocate: I believe that all software should be free—free to run as you please, to change, to share, and to share your changes.<br/>Participant: Won&rsquo;t you make less money because users can share copies of your software?<br/>Free Software Advocate: That&rsquo;s a possibility, yes. But you don&rsquo;t need to make the maximum amount of money, as long as you can comfortably pay the developers to make the software.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>This is an <em>entirely</em> different conversation. You see, the FSA and the Participant were never arguing over free software at all—they were arguing over whether a creator has the right to the maximum possible potential value created by their goods. In this version of the conversation, the Participant recognized a possible source of linguistic confusion, actively avoided the potential Pit Trap, and through that, both parties discovered the root cause of their disagreement—which had little to do with the mechanics of free software, where they would have become bogged down in previous iterations of the conversation.</p>

<h2>What Does This Mean for You?</h2>

<p>Here is the first and foremost lesson to be gleaned from this post:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>If you want to make your discussions productive, enforce linguistic clarity. Ensure that both parties properly understand what the other means by the terms they use.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>I will give you a personal, 100% unscientific guarantee that if you do this, you and those you talk with will learn significantly more from any debate, discussion, or argument that you have, and that you will spend less time arguing about meaningless details.</p>

<h2>Enforcing Linguistic Clarity: A How-To</h2>

<p>There is a single, powerful tool offered to you by language to improve linguistic clarity and avoid the potential Pit Trap: the question. Let&rsquo;s return to our earlier example, but assume the Participant is no longer being linguistically proactive:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Free Software Advocate: I believe that all software should be free—free to run as you please, to change, to share, and to share your changes.<br/>Participant: How can you make money if users can share copies of your software?<br/>Free Software Advocate: When you say, &ldquo;make money&rdquo;, what do you mean by that?</p></blockquote></p>

<p>The Participant may find this a shocking question. In fact, they may have never even considered it. If so, congratulations—you may have just avoided a potential pit trap! However, there&rsquo;s also a chance that the Participant is not able to understand how that term can have entirely different meanings, and could find themselves at a loss to answer your question. Let&rsquo;s iterate again.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Free Software Advocate: I believe that all software should be free—free to run as you please, to change, to share, and to share your changes.<br/>Participant: How can you make money if users can share copies of your software?<br/>Free Software Advocate: When you say, &ldquo;make money&rdquo;, what do you mean by that? I firmly believe you can &ldquo;make money&rdquo; off of software, but when I say it I mean that &ldquo;you can make a decent living, enough to pay your bills and live a comfortable life.&rdquo;</p></blockquote></p>

<p>You can even anticipate possible misunderstandings, and prevent them<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Free Software Advocate: I believe that all software should be free—free to run as you please, to change, to share, and to share your changes.<br/>Participant: How can you make money if users can share copies of your software?<br/>Free Software Advocate: When you say, &ldquo;make money&rdquo;, what do you mean by that? I firmly believe you can &ldquo;make money&rdquo; off of software, but when I say it I mean that &ldquo;you can make a decent living, enough to pay your bills and live a comfortable life.&rdquo; It might be possible to make more money if you didn&rsquo;t allow sharing it, but I don&rsquo;t think that making the most money possible should be the goal.</p></blockquote></p>

<h2>Enforcing Linguistic Clarity: Generalization</h2>

<p>The human mind is a pattern matching machine. Luckily, many potential pit traps follow a common pattern—therefore, we can train the mind to recognize these patterns, and avoid these traps.</p>

<p>In it&rsquo;s most general form, the pattern is often as such:</p>

<p>There exist a Participant and an Advocate. The Advocate firmly believes X, which relies on the assumption A. The Participant takes disagreement with X and begins to debate the details of the issue with the Advocate. The debate revolves around phrase P, which conveniently summarizes the issue.</p>

<p>From the Advocate&rsquo;s perspective, they&rsquo;ve been discussing X for years, and they&rsquo;ve always known A. Any discussion of X quite obviously implies assumption A—who would say phrase P without implying A? The Participant, on the other hand, can&rsquo;t understand why the Advocate is jumping to the ridiculous conclusion X—can&rsquo;t the Advocate see the idea is missing key elements that would make it valid?</p>

<p>The missing assumption A is the Pit Trap. The Advocate believes that through phrase P, the assumption A has been brought into the conversation. In reality, the Participant has probably never considered assumption A. In some cases, the Participant may even have a conflicting assumption Z that causes a more hostile argument while trapped in the Pit.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<h2>Enforcing Linguistic Clarity: Examples</h2>

<p>Pattern matching works most effectively when trained—so let us apply the above generalization to a few more very common examples of linguistic confusion. That way, in the future, you can learn to avoid miring your conversations in various Pit Traps. We will start by rigorously defining the Free Software example, and then move on to a few others.</p>

<h3>Free Software</h3>

<p>Trapped Version:
<blockquote><p>Advocate: I believe that all software should be free—free to run as you please, to change, to share, and to share your changes.<br/>Participant: How can you make money if users can share copies of your software?<br/>(Conversation enters the Pit)</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Safer Version:
<blockquote><p>Advocate: I believe that all software should be free—free to run as you please, to change, to share, and to share your changes.<br/>Participant: How can you make money if users can share copies of your software?<br/>Advocate: When you say, &ldquo;make money&rdquo;, what do you mean by that? I firmly believe you can &ldquo;make money&rdquo; off of software, but when I say it I mean that &ldquo;you can make a decent living, enough to pay your bills and live a comfortable life.&rdquo; It might be possible to make more money if you didn&rsquo;t allow sharing it, but I don&rsquo;t think that making the most money possible should be the goal.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Belief: All software should be free.
Assumption: The goal of making money off of software is to make enough money to pay the developer a comfortable wage in order to convince them to make the software.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>
Contradicting Assumption: The goal of making money off of software is to make as much money as possible in order to convince people to make software.[^4]
Phrase: &ldquo;make money&rdquo;</p>

<h3>Gender Identity/Transgenderism</h3>

<p>Trapped Version:
<blockquote><p>Participant: That person has a penis, so they are a man!<br/>Advocate: No, she is female. She told you so.<br/>(Conversation enters the Pit)</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Safer Version
<blockquote><p>Participant: That person has a penis, so they are a man!<br/>Advocate: When that person says that they are a woman, they&rsquo;re talking about their gender. I, and plenty of other people, use the words &ldquo;gender&rdquo; and &ldquo;sex&rdquo; to refer to different concepts. Sex refers to biological and physiological characteristics. Gender refers to societal roles and expectations. I think that someone&rsquo;s gender and sex can be different, and you should respect the gender identity they choose—including the pronouns they choose for themselves.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Note that in this issue there are two major assumptions to deal with, and after dealing with #1, it still would have been possible to become mired in #2.</p>

<p>Belief: Someone may have a penis but be a woman (or have any possible combinations of genitals and gender identities—I simply use a specific example for convenience).
Assumption: 1. Gender and sex are distinct terms 2. Someone may, and/or should be allowed to choose a gender different from their sex.
Contradicting Assumption: 1. Gender and sex are equivalent terms. 2. Even if #1 is not true, someone&rsquo;s gender cannot, and/or should not be allowed to be different than their sex.
Phrase: &ldquo;gender&rdquo;</p>

<h3>Other Common Examples</h3>

<p>There are a variety of other examples possible. This occurs most commonly when the discussion revolves around a word or phrase that has a variety of possible definitions that each carry their own nuances, but have deceptively similar subject areas. Examples like &ldquo;feminism&rdquo;, &ldquo;bad music&rdquo;, or the like can be particularly troublesome—people assume they have one definition (conveniently, the definition used by said person) and hold discussions with that assumption in their mind.</p>

<h2>In Conclusion</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to give a TL;DR here. This is a discussion that requires demonstration and nuance, and it would be doing a disservice to provide an incomplete picture. At the center of the issue is the problem that two people may mean entirely different concepts with the same or similar phrases—the adverse effects this can cause, and how to avoid them, can be read above.</p>

<p>For all of you who did read the post: go forth, be free, debate! Be on the lookout for when another participant may not be using the same defition for a term as you would—and ask! No longer be caught by frivolous arguments! Find the root cause of your disagreements! Good luck, and have fun!</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Before any snarky developer makes a comment about &ldquo;X software product isn&rsquo;t really free, it&rsquo;s just open source"—you&rsquo;re right. I&rsquo;m being convenient here. Look, linguistic confusion!<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>If you&rsquo;re paying close attention, this should be familiar—it&rsquo;s exactly what we did during the first iteration of our free software argument, when we added the definition of free software.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>One could argue that this post is not about linguistic confusion, but actually a difference in assumptions. That person would be mostly right. However, the fact that participants in a conversation have different assumptions is trivially true, and quite unhelpful—they can&rsquo;t possibly share every assumption they come with. By taking a linguistic perspective, you can equip yourself with a tool to identify where these assumptions lie, and correct for them, given that most if not all assumptions come connected to a word or phrase. After all, assumptions are just concepts, and words just tools for describing these concepts—but that subject could yield an entirely different post.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p>The observant may notice another layer of potential lingustic confusion within these assumptions: in one case &ldquo;convince people to make software&rdquo; seems to imply just convincing a developer that certain software should be made, while in the other &ldquo;convince people to make software&rdquo; seems to imply attracting the most amount of people to making software as is possible. This is a less insidious and unclear Pit Trap, but another one never-the-less. <a href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
